Guide to the New-York Historical Society Development Office Records 1956-2012 (bulk, 1982-1990s) NYHS-RG 25
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society Development Office records (RESTRICTED)
1956-2012 (bulk, 1982-1990s)
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 25
47.25 Linear feet in 68 boxes of various sizes and 5 boxes of oversize computer print-outs
The Development Office records include files concerning N-YHS's fundraising initiatives for exhibitions, collections conservation and preservation, cataloging, education programs, publications, physical plant improvements, general operating support, and other purposes. Sources of grants and other funds documented in the record group include government agencies, foundations, corporations, trustees, other individuals, memberships, and benefit events. The bulk of the records date from the 1980s and the early 1990s, with some files ranging back to the 1950s.The record group has not yet been vetted by the Development Office for public use and is therefore currently restricted.
Arrangement Note
The Development Office records are organized in six series:
Series I. Grants, 1974-1993
Series II. Subject Files, 1982-1997
Series III. Prospect & Donor Files, 1956-1996
Series IV. Contribution Records, 1983-1993
Series V. Membership Director's Records, 1983-1993
Series VI. Event Collateral Files, 1990s-2010s
Access Restrictions
The Development Office record group remains restricted because it has not been reviewed with the Office to determine which records may be made publicly available.
Materials are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society Development Office records (NYHS-RG 25) are as follows:
Both the New-York Historical Society Museum Department records (NYHS-RG 20) and the New-York Historical Society Library Department records (NYHS-RG 21) include files concerning grants and the grant-funded exhibitions, projects and other initiatives
Scope and Contents Note
The Development Office records include files concerning N-YHS's fundraising initiatives for exhibitions, collections conservation and preservation, cataloging, education programs, publications (including catalogues and the Encyclopedia of New York City), physical plant improvements, general operating support, and other purposes. Sources of grants and other funds documented in the record group include government agencies, foundations, corporations, trustees, other individuals, memberships, and benefit events (including the first History Makers galas, held in 1988 and 1989). The bulk of the records date from the 1980s to the 1990s, with some files ranging back to the 1950s.
The records include files of grant applications (both approved and declined) and related correspondence and reports, subject files for specific fundraising objectives and events, corporate and foundation prospect files, donor contribution records, and membership event and benefit logistical arrangements.
Accruals Note
Further accruals to the record group are expected over time.
Fund raising; Grants-in-aid.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society -- Benefactors.; New-York Historical Society -- Correspondence.; New-York Historical Society. Development Office
- Series I. Grants, 1974-1993; 7.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes grant applications and related instructions, correspondence, drafts, working files, acknowledgements, interim and final reports, and other documents. The files include both grant requests approved and declined/rejected. The grants pertain almost entirely to government grants, with only occasional reference to foundation or other private grants. These files include grant requests for conservation and preservation, cataloging, exhibitions, educational programs, and general operating support. The container list includes more specific references as to content at the box and folder level. The bulk of the material dates from the 1980s, especially the mid to late 1980s. A few files date from the late 1970s and early 1980s, and a few date from the early 1990s. Although the bulk of the files appear to have come from the Development Department, many of the files in the final box of the series, from the early 1990s, appear to have come from the files of N-YHS President Barbara Knowles Debs, and were likely moved here by a processing archivist in the early 2000s.
  Arrangement Note
  With minor exception, the files are in original order as found during processing in December 2016. Although the series is arranged by grant funding organization, there appear to be four rough sets of the files: first, a set of core files from the Development Office; second, a set of what appears to be mostly rejected applications; third, a set of various files likely found after the first two sets were boxed for storage; and a fourth with later (early 1990s) material. The Bond Act files, found separately by the processing archivist in 2016, were added to the end of the series.
  - New York Council for the Humanities (3 folders), 1983-1986 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-3)
    General Note
    Includes photo survey proposal (declined) and film on Theresa Bernstein.
  - New York City Department of Cultural Affairs (6 folders), 1985-1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4-9)
    Includes public services/programs and education funding.
  - New York State Council on the Arts (10 folders), 1986-1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-10)
    Includes exhibition planning, collections maintenance, Calyo audience survey, Luman Reed frames, paper conservation studio.
  - New York State Council on the Arts (7 folders), 1978-1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-7)
    Includes Bracklow, de Tocqueville, de Neuville, and other exhibitions, and furniture conservation.
  - Institute of Museum Services (IMS), 1989 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    Includes furniture conservation.
  - Institute of Museum Services (IMS) (2 folders), 1987-1989 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-2)
    Includes painting and paper conservation labs (includes floor plan).
  - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) (6 folders), 1982-1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3-8)
    Includes conservation (hot table), exhibitions (Niagara; Bracklow; American Landscape Painting, Genre Art & Drawing (includes photographs); and Nieuw Amsterdam), and development of a narrated slide presentation as an introduction to N-YHS's collections.
  - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) (8 folders), 1974-1981 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-8)
    Includes storage space renovation, Audubon installation, conservation of paintings, catalogue of paintings, survey and exhibitions of furniture and other decorative arts objects, and Manhattan Now exhibition.
  - New York State Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, 1989 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
    Includes mock Constitutional Conventions for school age students, an outgrowth of the Summer Institutes.
  - New York State Department of Education (3 folders), 1987-1989 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10-12)
    Includes Henry O'Reilly collection processing, American Art Union and Daniel Ullman preservation microfilming, and conservation of McComb City Hall drawings.
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) (4 folders), 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-4)
    Includes conservation of Nicolino Calyo paintings and funding for the exhibition Government by Choice: Inventing the U.S. Constitution, including photographs of documents used in the exhibition.
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) (2 folders), 1984 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-2)
    Includes newspaper cataloging and exhibition Centuries of Childhood in New York, including photographic contact sheets and negatives of the galleries.
  - Encyclopedia of New York City, 1985-1991 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
    Includes correspondence concerning fundraising for this project. See also the files below in Series II.B (Subject Files).
  - National Historical Publications Records Commission (NHPRC), 1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    Includes architectural collections.
  - Summer History Institute, 1986-1988 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
    Includes plans, proposals, correspondence, etc. related to general fundraising for the program.
  - United States Department of Justice. Sharing the Spirit (4 folders), 1988-1991 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-4)
    Includes programs funded by DOJ's Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, including the radio series "Constitution on the Air" and "The Bicentennial Connection."
  - United States Department of Education. Summer History Institute, 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
  - United States Department of Education. (7 folders), 1984-1988 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-7)
    Includes book, manuscript and map cataloging, Rufus King Library conservation and cataloging, and Landauer Collection conservation. Funding for some of these appears to have been declined.
  - Rejected Applications (11 of 13 folders), 1977-1987 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-11)
    All the files in this box appear to be unsuccessful or general information files. Includes NEH (U.S. photograph survey, Landauer collection, conservation survey, Luman Reed planning, Rivey painting conservation) and NEA (China Trade exhibition, paintings storage).
  - Rejected Applications (2 of 13 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-2)
    Includes NEA (paper conservation studio, architectural collections).
  - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) (2 folders), 1988-1990 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3-4)
    Includes conservation of Catlin drawings and exhibition 500 Years of American Clothing.
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), 1989 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
    Includes conservation planning for Audubon drawings (declined).
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) (5 folders), 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1-5)
    Includes physical plant renovations (declined), cataloging of silver collection (declined), and cataloging and preservation of Cass Gilbert collection.
  - New York State Department of Education (3 folders), 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-3)
    Includes conservation of McComb City Hall drawings and conservation of maps (declined).
  - United States Department of Education, 1988 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 4)
    Includes map cataloging.
  - Institute of Museum Services (IMS) (4 folders), 1982-1988 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 5-8)
    Includes general operating support and paper conservation studio.
  - New York State Council on the Arts (3 folders), 1976-1992 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1-3)
    Includes arts-in-education requests and "Why History?" and other programs.
  - New State State Library, 1992 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4)
    Includes acknowledgement of grant for conservation of Erskine-DeWitt maps.
  - New York State Council for the Humanities, 1989 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5)
  - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) (5 folders), 1989-1992 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 6-10)
    Includes Cass Gilbert, photograph database, and other proposals.
  - Institute of Museum Services (IMS) (3 folders), 1989-1993 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 11-13)
    Includes conservation and general operating support.
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) (8 folders), 1989-1992 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 14-21)
    Renovation of physical plant and collection re-housing/storage, book and pamphlet cataloging, negative preservation, Tenth Street Studio exhibition and publication, images of Indians exhibition, and establishment of endowments.
  - New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation (1 of 2 boxes), 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1-8)
    This box and the next concerns N-YHS's application and receipt of a grant under the Environmental Quality Bond Act of 1986 (EQBA) for preservation of its building, specifically roof restoration. The second box includes extensive photographs and slides of the roof, damage, etc.
  - New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation (2 of 2 boxes), 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1-6)
- Series VI. Event Collateral Files, 1990s-2010s; 4 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes a run of "collateral" documents related to fundraisers, History Makers Gala, invitation-only events (such as exhibition opening receptions, Strawberry Festival, etc.), and other events other than those for the general public. These materials date principally from 1998 to the 2010s. They include event programs, invitations, announcements, and the like. The series also includes assorted digital media (DVDs/CDs re: object images, programs, etc.), videocassettes, and audiocassettes.
  Arrangement
  The paper files of collateral material are arranged as received from the Development Office, which is by topic (general collateral, particular type of event, etc.), then chronological. The digital and audiovisual media are unsorted.
  - Event invitations, etc., 1990s-2010 (Offsite-box 70)
    Includes a few folders of miscellaneous invitations, brochures, etc. from the 1990s and into the early 2000s. The bulk of the box includes folders of material filed by year from 1998-2010.
  - Event invitations, etc., 2004-2012 (Offsite-box 71)
    Includes files of invitations and other collateral material for: a few exhibitions (2004-2010), opening of the Dimenna Children's Museum (2010), re-opening N-YHS post-renovation (2011), American Musicals Project (2012), Weekend with History (2006-11, with gaps), History Makers Gala (2004-2011), and Strawberry Festival (2004-2012). The box also holds packets of snapshots of events, though these are mostly unidentified.
  - Videocassettes, 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 72)
  - Videocassettes; Audiocassettes, Digital CDs/DVDs, 1990s-2010s (Offsite-box 73)